# André Filipe Silva

Porto, Porto, Portugal



andre3silva@outlook.com



linkedin.com/in/andrefilipesilva

# **Summary**

Human-centered design for Applications and Services, Digital Transformation and Software Architecture. Software development is an Art form, a craftsmanship process. +10 years working worldwide, I'm a specialist in Enterprise Architecture and Team management.

I am a Full-Stack Developer (React, Node.js, TypeScript, MongoDB, Google Cloud), Software Architect, Code Instructor and the Chief Technology Officer at Sioslife, currently living in Porto, Portugal. My interests range from technology to design. I am also an automotive and motorcycle enthusiast.

# **Experience**



# **Chief Technology Officer**

Sioslife

Jan 2022 - Present (1 year 10 months)

As a Technology Executive, I am responsible for the management of Sioslife's research and development (R&D) and its technological needs. I oversee the development and dissemination of technology for external customers, vendors, and other clients, helping to improve and increase business. My role also encompasses that of a Chief Information Officer, where I have the overall responsibility of managing the physical and personnel technology infrastructure, including technology deployment, network and system management, integration testing and personnel development. I manage client relations, ensuring service objectives and expectations are met. I also work closely with the Chief Product Officer, ensuring the best product definition and time estimation. As the Chief Software Architect and Lead Backend Developer, I lead the tech team and act as Scrum Master. Additionally, I provide guidance to developers to help them reach their full potential and complete their tasks on time with the best possible outcomes.

#### Tech Stack:

- TypeScript
- JavaScript
- CSS
- HTML 5
- React
- React Native
- Unity
- Node.is
- MongoDB
- Google Cloud Platform
- OpenAl
- Android OS Development
- iOS OS Development
- Microsoft Windows OS Development
- GitHub Actions



# **Software Engineering Manager**

#### Sioslife

Oct 2019 - Jan 2022 (2 years 4 months)

Sioslife is dedicated to creating a modern and inclusive society that harnesses technology to meet the needs of all its members. To ensure the best quality of life for senior citizens, Sioslife offers innovative and user-friendly interactive platforms that address the unique challenges of aging. As the manager of a development team made up of software developers and UI/UX designers, I am responsible for providing software architecture to ensure our products are of the highest quality.



# Freelance Software Engineer

Etecode - Academia de Tecnologia

2010 - Oct 2019 (9 years)

At the three-month mark of my Licentiate degree, I began to receive requests for software solutions. In response, I started working as a freelancer outside of working hours offering services such as consulting, problem analysis, requirements gathering, software development, and implementation. My goal with this endeavor was to take on the most extraordinary problems and situations that my full-time job would not provide.

Some examples were:

- Transform a PASCAL backoffice into a Microsoft ASP.NET web application
- Convert a COBOL system into a Node.js application
- Integrate an Accounting tool into a web platform
- Develop single code base mobile applications for Online stores across multiple operating systems
- Create an Image Recognition system for product labels that would replace the need for barcodes

# Solutions Architect and Senior Software Developer

MC

Mar 2017 - Sep 2019 (2 years 7 months)

Sonae is a multinational corporation that has built a strong culture of innovation and execution, enabling them to create value across multiple geographies and deliver the benefits of progress to more and more people. During my time at Sonae, I worked on a project to improve the logistics processes of Continente Online, an eCommerce platform, from order to delivery, including optimizing the picking process. I was responsible for designing and implementing solutions using Agile methodology, and I also lectured my colleagues from other teams in my specialties. I had the opportunity to be the code instructor for two bootcamps: CSS for Beginners and CSS Advanced. I eventually moved on from Sonae to seek a role with more Team Leadership responsibilities, as I felt the need to work with and inspire younger talent. Teck Stack:

- Microsoft .NET
- Microsoft .NET Core
- Microsoft Sharepoint
- Microsoft WCF
- Microsoft Forms
- Microsoft SQL Server
- Microsoft Team Foundation Server (TFS) (now known as Azure DevOps Server)
- Microsoft Azure
- HTML

- JavaScript
- CSS
- Agile

Code Instructor courses:

- CSS for Beginners
- CSS Advanced

#### Deloitte Tech Lead

# **Deloitte Digital**

Sep 2015 - Feb 2017 (1 year 6 months)

I worked as the Tech Lead for Deloitte Digital in the Porto Area of Portugal from September 2015 to February 2017. Deloitte Digital was a new concept for Portugal, and I was the first one to lead the charge in creating a 'disruptive' process that had never been seen before in the company. My job was to create a new software architecture stack that could deliver a range of products to insurance and banking customers. I was responsible for leading a distributed team in an Agile methodology and my daily tasks included talking with team members about their work and emotional state, helping them code and removing obstacles, designing and coding solutions myself, and responding to my manager's requests. I also created and took part in client workshops to gather software requirements and manage expectations using the Service Design Methodology. Additionally, I gave lectures to junior colleagues on a range of technologies such as JavaScript, Node.js, MongoDB, HTML, CSS, and User Experience Design (based on the book "The Design of Everyday Things" by Donald A. Norman). I also participated in an OutSystems Bootcamp and became a certified OutSystems Developer. Eventually, I left Deloitte due to the amount of travel and time away from my family that the position required.

#### Tech Stack:

- Angular
- HTML 5
- CSS
- JavaScript
- Node.is
- REST APIs
- Microservices
- MongoDB
- AWS Cloud Services
- BitBucket (Code versioning)
- BitBucket Pipelines
- Agile

Code Instructor courses:

- Career reconversion into Information Technology (Coding Frontend and Backend)
- User Experience Design

#### c|side Software Architect and Frontend Developer

#### **CSide Intelligent Solutions**

Jun 2015 - Sep 2015 (4 months)

I had the opportunity to create a new front-end product for CSide, a software house that provides services and applications for service providers, utilities and telecommunication companies. This project, which was expected to take six months, was completed in a mere three. The application was designed to be a responsive web solution, capable of running on both desktop and mobile devices, and was built on top of an existing WebAPI. To do this, I familiarized myself with both Angular 1 and 2 (beta at the

time) and constructed a full application in Angular 1 inside of a Microsoft ASP.NET MVC Web App. This project was my first experience as a Software Architect and User Experience Designer, and I am proud of the work I created, which included new services related to energy efficiency, end-user energy reports, smart grids, smart homes, gas and water consumption, heating metering and security and video surveillance.

#### Tech Stack:

- IoT Devices Integration
- Angular.js
- Angular (2)
- Microsoft ASP.NET
- User Experience Design
- Agile
- Microsoft Team Foundation Server (TFS) (now known as Azure DevOps Server)

# Software Architecture Analyst and Developer Engineer

# **VORTAL Connecting Business**

Jun 2014 - Jun 2015 (1 year 1 month)

Vortal is a world-renowned eSourcing and eProcurement platform that connects thousands of buyers with a global network of suppliers. As an analyst on the Vortal Software Architecture Team, I was responsible for providing input on new developments and bug fixes. Additionally, I worked as a Web Software Developer utilizing a Model-Driven-Architecture built in JAVA to convert XML to C# MVC. Our primary objective was to clone our existing platform for an on-premises version to be installed in Colombia. Additionally, I provided lectures and training to new members of the team. Upon completion of the project, I left Vortal with the majority of the team beginning new assignments.

#### Tech Stack:

- Microsoft .NET C#
- Java
- HTML 5
- CSS
- JavaScript
- Agile methodology
- Software Architecture Quality Assurance
- Frontend testing automation (Selenium)
- Jenkins (CI/CD)
- Git

# **Software Engineer and Product Designer**

#### **ELO Solutions**

Aug 2013 - Jun 2014 (11 months)

At ELO SI I was invited to join the team as their CTO, and with this new role I was tasked with the duty of managing Attendance and People (Human Capital). The company had recently made the transition from a Desktop to a Web Solution, and this had resulted in quite a few issues. The team I joined was not particularly knowledgeable in Web Development, and it was my objective to teach them the fundamentals and to fix any problems that arose. I was also able to work in tandem with companies such as Thales Portugal and Mota Engil in India, Brazil and Angola, creating new products and solutions. Eventually, I left ELO after successfully completing my duties and goals, looking for a bigger challenge with a larger team.

Teck Stack:

- Microsoft ASP.NET MVC
- Bootstrap
- CSS
- JavaScript
- ¡Query Mobile
- Microsoft .NET C#
- Microsoft .NET WPF
- Microsoft .NET Forms
- SignalR (WebSockets)
- HTML5 APIs (Geo Location, Offline Storage and others)
- Microsoft SQL Server
- Microsoft Team Foundation Server (TFS) (now known as Azure DevOps Server)

# Founder and Software Engineer

#### heavenware

Nov 2012 - Dec 2013 (1 year 2 months)

I was incredibly fortunate to have the opportunity to work on a Licence Degree thesis that involved creating a Sports Management Web Platform for "Escolas da Academia do Sporting Clube de Portugal". Working with a colleague to develop the client's needs was an incredibly enriching experience as I had the chance to understand the language they used, translate their needs into use cases, and build and implement an architecture from the ground up. At the end of the thesis, we were presented with the option of turning our project into a funded start-up; however, we decided to forego it in favor of gaining more experience in the market and securing a more stable job.

#### Tech Stack:

- Microsoft ASP.NET MVC
- Microsoft .NET C#
- HTML 5
- CSS
- JavaScript
- jQuery
- Web Services
- SignalR
- Android OS Development
- Windows Phone Development
- Microsoft Entity Framework
- SVN

### **Education**



#### Instituto Superior de Engenharia do Porto

Master's degree, Informatics, Graphical Systems and Multimedia - Software Engineering

2013 - 2015

The Masters in Computer Engineering aims to deepen the knowledge in Computer Engineering, from a scientific and technological base conferred by a Degree in Computer Science or similar. The course aims to train qualified professionals to practice as a Informatics Engineering with high scientific quality, technical, ethical and human relations in the broad spectrum of job profiles identified for Informatics Engineering. The course still provides to its students an education that by its cohesion and solidity,

enable those who wish to pursue careers as Phd researchers. In order to align this MSc with the market demand, the course offers a flexible and heterogeneous curriculum structure organized in three branches of specialization:

- -Architecture, Systems and Networks
- -Graphics and Multimedia Systems
- -Knowledge and Decision Technologies.

# Instituto Superior de Engenharia do Porto

Licentiate degree, Informatics

2010 - 2013

Informatics Engineering at ISEP takes a distinctive approach to learning, in order to produce high quality software engineers that are highly sought by the market. ISEP it is a member of the MIT lead CDIO consortium (www.cdio.org) and Informatics Engineering is the CDIO flagship program at ISEP. Engineering is about making things, thus students at ISEP have a solid practical experience, with a group project at the end of each semester and a capstone project/internship at the end of the program.

### **Licenses & Certifications**

- Associate Developer OutSystems
- Advanced Java Oracle
- **Exam 480: Programming in HTML5 with JavaScript and CSS3** Microsoft
- **Emotional Intelligence** Instituto Superior de Engenharia do Porto
- **Exam 486: Developing ASP.NET MVC Web Applications** Microsoft
- **MCSA: Web Applications Certified 2017** Microsoft
- MCSD: App Builder Certified 2018 Microsoft
- Exam 532: Developing Microsoft Azure Solutions Microsoft

### **Skills**

TypeScript • Team Leadership • Usability • System Architecture • User Experience • Software Design Patterns • Software Engineering • Software Project Management • Software Design • Software Development

### **Honors & Awards**

National Merit Scholarship - Direção Geral do Ensino Superior - Portugal Feb 2015

Direção Geral do Ensino Superior Merit Scholarship in 2011/2012

County Best Student Scholarship - Camara Municipal de Paredes - Porto, Portugal Feb 2014
County Best Student in College 2011/2012

County Best Student Scholarship - Camara Municipal de Paredes - Porto, Portugal Feb 2013
County Best Student in College 2010/2011